Finding aid for Joseph Ralston Hayden Papers, 1899-1945 [microfilm]
Bentley Historical Library
Joseph Ralston Hayden papers
1899-1945
Bentley Historical Library
Hayden, Joseph Ralston, 1887-1945
2011165 mf603c-615c
13 microfilms
The original collection (Donor no. 3109 ) came to the library in three principal accessions: 1955, 1971, and 1985. The microfilm copies were made at the request of different researchers.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Joseph Ralston Hayden was born on September 24, 1887 in Quincy, Illinois. He received his B.S. from Knox College in 1910, then his M.A. and Ph.D. from the University of Michigan in 1911 and 1915 respectively. From 1910 to 1912, while a student, Hayden was an assistant in American history at the University of Michigan. In 1912, he became a member of the university's department of political science, where he remained, except for his service with the government, until his death on May 19, 1945.
During World War I, Hayden was a lieutenant in the Michigan Naval Militia serving as senior officer of the University of Michigan division. He was in active service from April 1917 to February 1919. Following the war, Hayden returned to the University of Michigan.
Hayden was a recognized authority on the Philippine Islands. In this, Hayden was carrying on a tradition begun by Dean C. Worcester, who, like Hayden, was both on the faculty of the University of Michigan and called to public service in the Philippine Islands because of his expertise and experience. In 1922-23, Hayden was an exchange professor at the University of the Philippines; in 1930-31, he was the Carnegie Visiting Professor in the State University of the Philippines. In 1922-23, 1926, and 1930-31, Hayden was special correspondent in the Far East for the Christian Science Monitor. Hayden used each of these opportunities to travel in the islands, to study, and to make contacts with Philippine citizens, both government officials and private citizens.
In recognition of his learning and wide experience in Philippine matters, President Franklin Roosevelt appointed Hayden to serve as vice governor of the Philippines and secretary of public instruction. His choice for governor general, Frank Murphy, though possessing administrative skills and political charm, was coming to the Philippines without any real knowledge of the actualities of Filipino life and custom, and thus Roosevelt's reasoning for pairing Hayden with the former Detroit mayor. Hayden responded admirably to his selection by the president, performing his duties efficiently, even serving as acting governor general when Murphy returned to the United States for a six-month period.
With the establishment of the Philippine Commonwealth in 1935, Hayden returned to the University of Michigan, where he taught and worked on what would be his classic work The Philippines: A study in national development (1941). Following his return, Hayden was named James Orin Murfin Professor of Political Science and chairman of the department.
Hayden returned to public service with the outbreak of World War II, where his knowledge of the Philippines proved invaluable. From 1941 to 1945, he worked with the U.S. Office of the Coordinator of Information and, after June 1942, with its successor organization, the Office of Strategic Services. From 1943 to 1945, Hayden was named civil adviser and consultant on Philippine affairs with the U.S. War Department, attached to the staff of General Douglas MacArthur. As part of this later activity, Hayden developed and headed up as chief a special staff section of the United States Armed Forces for the Far East - the Philippine Research and Information Section. The role he envisioned for the Philippine Research and Information Section was three-fold: to prepare reports and studies about the Philippines; to distribute information about the Philippines as needed; and to collect books, magazines, newspapers, and printed and manuscript materials about the Philippines with a view to their "effectiveness in furthering the prosecution of the war."
As vice governor of the Philippine Islands during the 1930s, and later as advisor on Philippine affairs to General Douglas MacArthur during World War II, Joseph R. Hayden was recipient of much substantive documentation relating to the American phase of Philippine Island history. Hayden was an astute and discerning scholar of Philippine life and history, and as such used the opportunity of his frequent trips to the Far East to collect materials (official and personal) that he knew would be of value in his teaching and research, and that he also hoped would prove useful to scholars following after him. The Philippine Collection is the heart of the collection comprising more than 75% of the Hayden papers. These files are testimony to Hayden's foresight in drawing together official documents (because of the positions he held) and other records (sent to him because of his known interest in the Philippines). These collected materials include official reports, minutes of meetings attended, memoranda with government officials, photographs, clippings, and published materials.
Over the years, researchers, unable to examine the originals, have requested microfilm copies of portions of the Hayden papers. This finding aid lists those files that have been microfilmed and which are available for inter-library loan. The bulk of these files date from the 1920s and relate in great part to the Philippine politics and to the affairs of the provinces. Many of the files relate to the Moros and to Mindanao and Sulu. The finding aid to the original collection is also available through the library's homepage.
Mindanao Island (Philippines); Philippines -- History -- 1898-1946.; Sulu Archipelago (Philippines); Muslims -- Philippines.; Hayden, Joseph Ralston, 1887-1945.
- Philippine collection
  - Economic
    - Agriculture and Material Resources
      - Agriculture (Reel Mf603)
        - Report, 1926 (Reel Mf603)
          (14-6)
      - Rubber production
        - Clippings, 1928 (Reel Mf603)
          (14-8)
    - Government Finance
      - Miscellaneous economic topics
        - Transportation and communication, report about, 1926 (Reel Mf603)
          (16-8)
  - Education
    - Luther Parker case, 1926 (Reel Mf604)
      (16-18)
  - Political
    - Political Parties
      - Sakdals
        - Papers about, 1934-1935 (Reel Mf605)
          (25-23, etc.-25-26; and 25-29)
        - Clippings about, 1935-1937 (Reel Mf606)
          (25-27; 25-28)
        - Clippings about, 1937-1940 (Reel Mf606)
          (26-1, etc. 26-3)
  - Provincial
    - Agusan
      - Reports about, 1933-1935 (Reel Mf603)
        (27-24; 27-25)
    - Batanes
      - Papers about, 1934-1935 (Reel Mf603)
        (27-26)
    - Bakidnon
      - Papers about, 1934-1935 (Reel Mf603)
        (27-27)
    - Cotabato
      - Reports about, 1926; 1934-1935 (Reel Mf603)
        (27-28; 27-31; 27-32)
      - Papers about, 1933-1935 (Reel Mf603)
        (27-29; 27-30; 27-33)
    - Davao
      - Memoranda of J.C. Early about, 1930 (Reel Mf603)
        (28-1)
      - Japanese in Davao
        - Report relating to, 1926 (Reel Mf603)
          (28-2)
        - Japanese interests in, 1934-1935 (Reel Mf603)
          (28-4)
      - Papers about, 1931 (Reel Mf603)
        (28-3)
      - Reports of the Provincial Governor, 1935 (Reel Mf603)
        (28-5)
    - Lanao
      - Reports of the Provincial Governor, 1932-1937 (Reel Mf607)
        (28-6; 28-7; 28-8)
      - Report relating to the Moro problem, 1933 (Reel Mf607)
        (28-9)
      - Letter from J.J. Heffington about, 1930 (Reel Mf607)
        (28-10)
      - Papers about, 1933-1935 (Reel Mf607)
        (28-11; 28-12; 28-13)
      - Clippings about, 1931-1936 (Reel Mf607)
        (28-14, etc.-28-17)
      - Reports about, 1933; 1935 (Reel Mf607)
        (28-18)
    - Zamboango
      - Reports of the Provincial Governor, 1934-1935 (Reel Mf607)
        (28-19)
      - Reports about, 1931 (Reel Mf607)
        (28-20)
      - Papers about, 1934-1935 (Reel Mf608)
        (28-21)
    - Bureau of Non-Christian Tribes
      - Reports of the Director, 1934-1935 (Reel Mf608)
        (28-22)
      - Clippings about, 1931-1935 (Reel Mf608)
        (28-23)
      - Papers about, 1934 (Reel Mf608)
        (28-24)
      - Papers about non-Christian tribes, 1934-1935 (Reel Mf608)
        (28-25)
    - Moros
      - Correspondence about, 1926 (Reel Mf608)
        (28-26)
      - Constabulary reports about, 1920-1933 (Reel Mf608)
        (28-27)
      - Reports about, 1929-1931 (Reel Mf608)
        (28-8; 28-9)
      - Memorandum about, 1933 (Reel Mf608)
        (28-30)
      - Papers about, 1933-1939 (Reel Mf608)
        (28-31; 28-33)
      - Governmental reorganization, 1934 (Reel Mf608)
        (28-32)
      - Clippings about, 1931-1935 (Reel Mf608)
        (28-34)
      - Clippings about, 1936-1937; 1940 (Reel Mf608)
        (29-1, etc.-29-4)
    - Mindanao and Sulu
      - Report about, 1930 (Reel Mf608)
        (29-5)
      - Colonization of, 1934-1935 (Reel Mf608)
        (29-6)
      - Development of
        - Papers about, 1930 (Reel Mf608)
          (29-7)
        - Report about, 1934 (Reel Mf608)
          (29-8)
      - Clippings about, 1936; 1939-1940 (Reel Mf608)
        (29-9; 29-10)
      - Report of the Commissioner for Mindanao and Sulu, 1937 (Reel Mf608)
        (29-11)
    - Mindanao
      - Clippings about, 1937 (Reel Mf608)
        (29-12)
      - Settlement of Mindanao, papers about, 1939 (Reel Mf608)
        (29-13)
    - Sulu
      - Report of the Provincial Governor, 1929; 1932; 1935-1937 (Reel Mf609)
        (29-14; 29-15; 29-20)
      - Monthly reports of the Provincial Governor, 1934-1935 (Reel Mf609)
        (29-16, etc.-29-19)
      - Government employment survey for Sulu, papers about, 1931-1934 (Reel Mf609)
        (29-21; 29-22)
      - Public health, report on, 1934 (Reel Mf609)
        (29-23)
      - Education, papers about, 1934-1935 (Reel Mf609)
        (29-24)
      - Budget, papers about, 1934 (Reel Mf609)
        (29-25)
      - Speech of J.R. Hayden entitled "The Government of Sulu Archipelago,", 1936 (Reel Mf609)
        (29-26)
      - James Fugate, provincial governor
        - Correspondence of, 1910-1937 (Reel Mf609)
          (29-27, etc.-29-31)
        - Petition relating to, 1935 (Reel Mf609)
          (29-32)
      - Arthur Spiller
        - Papers relating to, 1934-1935 (Reel Mf609)
          (29-33)
        - Papers relating to charges brought against him, 1933-1934 (Reel Mf609)
          (29-34)
      - Report of Major Charles S. Livingston entitled "Constabulary Monograph of the Sulu Province", 1915 (Reel Mf610)
        (29-35)
      - Alagar affairs on Sulu, clippings concerning, 1932 (Reel Mf610)
        (29-36)
      - Amoks on Sulu, papers about, 1934 (Reel Mf610)
        (30-1)
      - Moros on Sulu
        - Papers about, 1934-1935 (Reel Mf610)
          (30-2, etc.-30-5)
      - Report, 1928 (Reel Mf610)
        (30-6)
      - Memorandum, 1933 (Reel Mf610)
        (30-7)
      - Papers concerning province of Sulu, 1934-1935 (Reel Mf610)
        (30-8; 30-9)
      - Clippings concerning province of Sulu, 1934-1935 (Reel Mf610)
        (30-11)
      - Seminar papers concerning the Moros (Reel Mf610)
        (30-12)
- File maintained by Lloyd Millegan
  - Sulu and North Borneo areas, report about written by Captain J.A. Hamner, Philippine Regional Section, Allied Intelligence Bureau, 1943-1944 (Reel Mf611)
    (41-3)
  - JRH's mission to China and Australia for the Office of Strategic Services, papers about (Reel Mf613)
    (41-5)
  - Memorandum of conferences with MacArthur, Willoughby, and Merle-Smith regarding O.S.S. operations in the Southwest Pacific Area (Reel Mf613)
    (41-7)
  - China and JRH's activities in Chungking, China in 1942 papers about, 1940-1944 (Reel Mf613)
    (41-8)
  - Co-ordinator of Information and the Office of Strategic Services, papers about, 1941-1942 (Reel Mf612)
    (41-10)
  - Trip to China, reports and notes concerning, 1942-1943 (Reel Mf612)
    (41-12)
  - Memo from JRH relating to a memorandum to Colonel Donovan from Pearl Buck discussing the role of China in the war effort, 1942 (Reel Mf613)
    (41-16)
  - Statement of Edward M. Kuder written to JRH on events and conditions in Lanao immediately preceding the war and from, 1941-1943; 1943 (Reel Mf610)
    (includes appendices on the problems of government in predominately Moslem provinces)
    (41-17)
  - Preliminary report entitled "Philippine Civil Affairs: Policy and Organization", April 16, 1945 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-1)
  - Notes of conversations with General Douglas MacArthur, 1944-1945 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-2)
  - Notes of conversations with Manuel Quezon, including drafts of statement on conferences, March 1944 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-3)
  - Miscellaneous notes and directives from Manuel Quezon, 1944 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-4)
  - Question of presidential succession in the Philippines, copies of correspondence between Quezon, Osmena, and Roosevelt, 1943 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-5)
  - Evolution of a civil affairs policy for the Philippines, papers concerning, 1943-1944 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-6)
  - Philippine collaboration, papers concerning, 1945 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-7)
  - Treatment of American POW's and civilian internees in the Philippines, papers concerning, 1945 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-8)
  - Status and duties of the Commonwealth Government, the Commander-in-Chief, and the High Commissioner upon reoccupation, papers concerning (Reel Mf614)
    (42-9)
  - Report: "Principles governing arrangements for civil administration and jurisdiction in Netherlands Territory in the southwest Pacific area" (Reel Mf614)
    (42-10)
  - Telegrams of condolence upon the death of Manuel Quezon, August 1944 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-11)
  - Continuance of Quezon as Commonwealth President after November 1943 papers concerning, 1943 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-12)
  - Constitutional status of the Philippines during the war, paper written by UM Law School dean Henry M. Bates, papers about, 1943 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-13)
  - Provincial government of Palawan, report concerning, 1944 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-14)
  - Report of the Philippine Research and Information Section, April 1945 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-15)
  - Report entitled "Who's Who in the Philippines", September 1944 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-16)
  - Bibliography of Philippine materials in the Library of the Files and Studies Section, G-5, October 1944 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-17)
  - "Philippine Biographies,", October 1944 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-18)
  - Directory of Philippine Commonwealth Officials, April 1945 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-19)
  - Report entitled "Conditions Affecting Domestic Order in the Moro Provinces of Mindanao and Sulu", August 1945 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-20)
  - "The Philippines during the Japanese Regime and annotated list of the literature published in or about the Philippines during the Japanese Occupation", 1942-1945 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-21)
  - Guest log of the Philippine Research and Information Section, December 1944-April 1945 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-22)
  - Philippine Research and Information Section, miscellaneous papers about (Reel Mf614)
    (42-23)
  - Report by Hernando Abaya entitled "Collaboration & Collaborators, Philippine Version", May 1945 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-24)
  - Report entitled "Law Enforcement in the Philippine Islands", September 1944 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-25)
  - Report presenting a plan for the establishment of a constabulary force in Moro areas upon reoccupation, October 1944 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-26)
  - Plan presented by Lloyd Millegan for the cultural reorganization of the Philippines, April 1945 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-27)
  - Plan for psychological warfare in the southwest Pacific area, July 1944 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-28)
  - Reports of conferences between Jose Laurel and the Japanese, 1944 (Reel Mf614)
    (42-29)
  - Report of Chick Parsons to Manuel Quezon concerning the Philippine situation; and Quezon's reply, September 1943 (Reel Mf615)
    (42-30)
  - Memo concerning evacuees from the Philippines, September 1943-August 1944 (Reel Mf615)
    (42-31)
  - Papers concerning civilian internees in Santo Tomas prison camp, 1943 (Reel Mf615)
    (42-32)
  - Report entitled "Local Problems: Pangasinan Province, 26 April 1945" (Reel Mf615)
    (42-33)
  - Report entitled "The Hukbalahap", March 1945 (Reel Mf615)
    (42-34)
  - Report concerning Makapili and Ganaps in Nueva Ecija, February 1945 (Reel Mf615)
    (42-35)
  - History of USAFIP, North Luzon and guerrilla activities in North Luzon, February 1945 (Reel Mf615)
    (42-36)
  - Reports from Dionisio Gutierrez, including material on guerrilla activities in Mindanao, 1944-1945 (Reel Mf615)
    (42-37)
  - Correspondence of Lt. Commander F.L. Worcester concerning the guerrilla situation in Mindanao, 1943-1944 (Reel Mf615)
    (42-38)
  - Draft of speech entitled "The Philippines will not be conquered" (Reel Mf615)
    (42-39)
  - Paper entitled "The Philippine Public Schools: A brief appraisal" (Reel Mf615)
    (42-41)
  - Death of Manuel Quezon, papers concerning, 1944-1945 (Reel Mf615)
    (42-42)
  - Death of Sergio Osmena, papers concerning, 1944 (Reel Mf615)
    (42-43)
  - Miscellaneous personal papers, 1944-1945 (Reel Mf615)
    (42-44; 42-45)
  - Malolos Constitution (original copy), 1899 (Reel Mf615)
    (42-46)